A Guide to the Records of the Charlottesville School Board 1869-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: General Desegregation
  - Oversize broadside sponsored by the Committee for Public Education 1959 April 22, 1 item
    One broadside with two articles from The Lynchburg News, one written by John S. Battle, Jr. "Scholarship Program May Result In Even More Integration" and "Mr. Battle Speaks Out."
  - Organizations: General Assembly Special Session 1959 May 6, 7, 1 item (Box-folder 3:23)
    Notes from the Attorney General's office that instructed the School Board to show the total number of children residing in the city multiplied by the cost to the city for their education; money for scholarships; and money for school operations
  - Organizations: National Education Association Survey 1959 January 9, 1 item (Box-folder 3:24)
    Superintendent Ellis completed a survey on the effect of the closed schools on students, teachers and public attitudes.
  - Organizations: Parent's Committee for Emergency Schooling 1958-1959, 6 items (Box-folder 3:25)
    The organization was formed to offer temporary education during the closing of the schools. There are articles of Incorporation, mission of the group, and a petition asking that the local authorities be allowed to handle the school situation.
  - Organizations: Pupil Placement Board 1956-1959, 4 items (Box-folder 3:26)
    There is a telegram from the PPB informing the School Board that the placement board would assign the pupils. The School Board decided to file a motion questioning their authority. Also included is a list of procedures for pupil placements.
  - Organizations: Pupil Placement Board Applications 1956-1958, 1 group of applications (Box-folder 3:27)
    Applications for placement of pupils approved by the board for the school session 1956-1957, 1957-1958, and 1959-1960.
  - Organizations: Pupil Placement Board Applications 1956-1958, 1 group of applications (Box-folder 3:28)
    Applications for placement of pupils approved by the Pupil Placement Board for school session 1956-1957, 1957-1958, and 1959-1960.
  - Desegregation Organizations: Pupil Scholarship Funds 1958-1963, 1 notebook (Box-folder 4:1)
    There are reports that depict the names and number of students who were recipients; the private schools that they attended; and the net costs to the City and State.
  - Organizations: Southern Regional Council Reports 1959-1962, 21 articles (Box-folder 4:2)
    Southern Regional Council was organized in 1919 to fight racial injustice in the South.
    Articles included are: Report No. L-6 on the "The 'Davis Report' and the Truth about the Public School situation in Washington, D. C." 1959, July 3; Report No. L-8 on "Race and Intelligence" (Eighteen of the "Country's leading psychologists and anthropologists" issued comments about the equality of the races) 1959 August 10; Report No. L-9 on "The Private School Answer to the Desegregation Crisis The Virginia Experience" 1959 September 1; Report No. L-13 "Did you find that there was much difference in the ability of Negro children to receive and profit by instruction?" December 15, 1959;Report No. L-14 "A Report From Virginia" 1960 February 15; Report L-15 "Types of Desegregation Plans" can be found under Desegregation Plans in Other Areas 4:15; Report L-16 on "Atlanta and Washington Racial Differences in Academic Achievement by Frank H. Stallings 1960 February 26 Printed?; Report No. L-17 "Desegregation and Academic Achievement, March 14, 1960; Report No. L-19 "What Price Tag for 'Massive Resistance?" (by Frank Trippett Reprinting from St. Petersburg Times) October 14, 1960; Report No. L-20 Problem Solving Through Race Relations 1960 October 25; Report No. L-21 "Public Schools and community Development" 1960 November 30; Report No. L-22 Memorandum "To Florida Leaders In Civic, Religious, and Business Affairs" 1960 December 9;Special Report 19 "Sanctuaries for Tradition: Virginia's New Private Schools" 1961 February 8; Report No. L-24 Addresses by businessmen in Atlanta, and New Orleans 1960-1961; Report No. L-26 Address from General Lucius D. Clay at the Governor's Conference on Trade and Commerce in Atlanta, Georgia 1961 July 25; Report No. L-31 Wall Street Journal article, "Slipping Segregation: Negroes Win Lowering of More Barriers in South" 1962 February 6; Report No. L-32 Commentary by Dr. William P. Sullivan of Carleton Putnam's book, Race and Reason: A Yankee View. 1962 March 9; Report No. L-33 "A Statement of Recommended Police Policy Resulting from the New York University Graduate School of Public Administration Conference on 'The Challenge of Desegregation for the American Police Executive" 1962 March 9; Report No. L-34-A "Desegregation of Southern Parochial Schools" 1963 August 19; Report No. L-45on "Public Education in Mississippi" 1963 August 19
  - Organizations. State Board of Education Statement. 1955 December 13, 1 item (Box-folder 4:3)
    The board wanted the Constitutional Convention to amend Section 141 (which barred the use of public funds for private education) and would allow the schools to use tuition grants to send "white" children to all "white" schools.
  - Organizations United States Commission on Civil Rights. March 1, 1960, 1 item (Box-folder 4:4)
    There is written statement by Superintendent Ellis describing the events in Charlottesville following the decision of the Supreme Court in Brown v. Board of Education.
  - Organizations Virginia Congress of Parents and Teachers Resolution 1956 May 4, 1 item (Box-folder 4:5)
    There is a resolution that urged the Governor to call a special meeting of the General Assembly to establish legislation that would provide guidelines in resolving the issues with desegregation.
  - Organizations Virginia Council on Human Relations n. d., 3 items (Box-folder 4:6)
    There is a letter to Superintendent Ellis from John H. Marion, introducing Ellis to the VCHR, which supported desegregation. Also included are letters from the American Council on Human Relations.
  - Organizations. Virginia Education Association Statement 1955 December 11, 1 item (Box-folder 4:7)
    There is a statement from the General Assembly inviting the citizens of Virginia to vote on a constitutional convention that would allow the state to financially support private schools with tuition grants and amend Section 141.
  - Petition from the NAACP 1964, 5 items (Box-folder 4:8)
    There is a petition requesting an end to racial segregation signed by three hundred and six residents. There is also letter from the Superintendent of Schools, George C. Tramontin to John S. Battle, Jr. asking for advice on how to respond.
  - Plans for desegregation of Charlottesville Schools 1957-1959, 10 items (Box-folder 4:9)
    Included is a proposed plan for "Desegregation in the Charlottesville Schools" by Eunice M. Jackson with a map of school districts. There are also policies listed for the pupil placement plans, and suggestions from Judge John Paul titled, "Reorganization of Charlottesville Schools to which Negroes Have Been Assigned." There is also a paper by Dr. B. J. Chandler and Dr. Douglas S. Ward, "A Plan for the Preservation of the Virginia Public School System," and a memo on the meaning and implications of "deliberate speed." See also 3:17 Minutes of the Charlottesville School Board and Desegregation Plan 1959 February 18.
  - Plans for desegregation in other areas 1954-1960, 9 items (Box-folder 4:10)
    There are descriptions of desegregation plans for cities in Kentucky, Tennessee, Maryland, Arkansas, Virginia, Texas, and Georgia. Included is also the "Wise Plan for the Maintenance of Segregated Education in Virginia."
  - Plans for Desegregation requested by other school officials. 1958-1962, 27 items (Box-folder 4:11)
    Included are some questions relating to the Gray Commission School Plan.
  - Report on "Public School Desegregation Charlottesville, Virginia 1955-1962" by Paul Gaston and Thomas T. Hammond 1955 1962, 1 item (Box-folder 4:12)
    Report on the history of desegregation and the attitudes of the community in Charlottesville.
  - Resolutions 1955, October 13 and 1956 July 16, 2 items (Box-folder 4:13)
    Resolution to appeal the recent decision of the District Court of the United States for the Western District of Virginia and a resolution to reply to Oliver W. Hill's petition.
  - Resolution n. d., 1 item (Box-folder 4:14)
    Resolution that the President of the United States be urged to provide leadership in the school crisis confronting Virginia following the Supreme Court ruling in Brown v. Board of Education
  - Speeches by John S. Battle Jr. 1959 April 20 and April 22, 7 items (Box-folder 4:15)
  - Speeches by Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr. 1959 August 29, 1 item (Box-folder 4:16)
    Included are excerpts from the speech by Senator Harry F. Byrd at his 37 th Annual Orchard Picnic, Berryville, Virginia. Senator Byrd mentioned the closed schools in Prince Edward County. He also spoke about his opposition to the visit from Krushschev, and the Warren Commission.
  - Statement by Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr. 1956 January 9, 1 item (Box-folder 4:17)
    Senator Byrd issued a statement in support of calling the Constitutional Convention.
  - Statement by Dowell J. Howard, Superintendent of Public Instruction 1954 June 7 and 1956 January, 2 items (Box-folder 4:18)
    Superintendent Howard supported the calling of the Constitutional Convention and the amendment to Section 141.
  - Statement of the Declaration of Constitutional Principles 1956 March 12, 1 item (Box-folder 4:19)
    The Declaration which was to be presented to the Senate, criticized the decision of the Supreme Court in Brown vs. Board of Education
- Series III: Correspondence
  - A. Correspondence Legal
    - Correspondence Legal 1923; 1943; 1955; 1960, 10 items (Box-folder 5:1)
      Correspondents include Harris Hart, Superintendent of Public Instruction; Superintendent James G. Johnson; Major John Graves, City Attorney; and Walter F. George. Topics mentioned are a bond issue; County Unit Law and the abolishment of District School Boards; outline of the history of the city and county; and the United States Senate Committee on Finance and tax legislation.
    - Correspondence Legal Annexation Suit Charlottesville v. Albemarle 1961 September 8, 1 item (Box-folder 5:2)
      The city and county reached a compromise in a motion filed by the city to annex land in the county.
    - Correspondence Legal Michael & Dent 1969-1973, 45 items (Box-folder 5:3)
      Correspondents include James Harry Michael, Jr. and Superintendent Dr. Edward W. Rushton. Topics include James Harry Michael's speech to the Senate; kindergarten enrollment; pupil transportation; hearing and speech programs; twenty year old pupils; sick leave policies; Barksdale felony case; names for Charlottesville High School; bus monitors; and merging county and city school districts. There is also a "vote for Michael for Lt. Governor" autographed card.
    - Correspondence Legal 1974, 45 items (Box-folder 5:4)
      Correspondents include Dr. William J. Ellena, Paul M. Peatross, Jr., and Senator James Harry Michael, Jr. Topics mentioned are a legal case about the naming of Charlottesville High School; salaries of School Board members; relocation of VEPCO lines; maternity leave, budget crisis including a comment from Senator James Harry Michael, Jr. that this was "the roughest [session] I have yet served in; House Bill 373 on employee retirement benefits; Southern States payment; injections for students in an emergency situation; hospital bill for a student who was burned at Lane High School; altercation after a basketball game; a deed granting ownership of the McGuffey School to the City; suit against Pastor Frederick Patrick; and the widening of Preston Avenue.
    - Correspondence Legal 1975, 30 items (Box-folder 5:5)
      Correspondents include Senator James Harry Michael, Jr. and Superintendent Dr. William J. Ellena. Topics mentioned are successful negotiations with VEPCO; suspension of students at Buford; permission to name truant students in the newspaper; search and seizure of student property; salary of a principal after a sabbatical; dismissal of a teacher; instructional television, Virginia High School League and the North Western District from the Commonwealth, lease of Lane High School; and a Superintendent's right to his own legal counsel.
    - Correspondence Legal 1976, 33 items (Box-folder 5:6)
      Correspondents mentioned are Paul M. Peatross, Senator James Harry Michael, Jr. the Reverend Henry B. Mitchell; J. Page Williams; Michael & Dent, LTD.; Dr. Marvin C. Sutphin, and Dr. William J. Ellena. Topics are the Virginia High School League and the Northwest Region of the Commonwealth; personnel issues; sabbatical leave; federally funded teachers; nepotism; probation of wrestling coach; by-laws for the student School Board; conflict of interest of a School Board member (Family Services); bidding for school pictures; loaning money to students in emergency situations; collective bargaining and the Charlottesville Education Foundation, and a bidding process for the Yellow Transit Company.
    - Correspondence Legal 1977, 28 items (Box-folder 5:7)
      Correspondents include Senator James Harry Michael, Jr., and Attorney General Anthony F. Troy. Topics mentioned are a legal case, International Brotherhood of Teamsters v. United States, et al.; Federal judgeship for James Harry Michael, Jr.; unused funds; sale of land from the Technical Education Center; advertising on the athletic field score board; deed for the sale of Lane High School; conflict of interest for a School B oard member; contract for Yellow Transit Company; unemployment and insurance matters; and a lawsuit involving a professor with sabbatical leave.
    - Correspondence Legal Michael & Dent 1979, 35 items (Box-folder 5:8)
      Correspondents mentioned are Leroy Bruton, Dr. John S. Wright, Rayner V. Snead, Jr., John L. Snook, Raymond Bell, and Attorney General Marshall Coleman. Topics mentioned are new statutes in the Virginia Freedom of Information Act; the Virginia Code and conflict of interests; open School Board meetings; the length of School Board terms; right of access to a students' files; the retirement age changed to 70; federally funded research; by-laws for the Piedmont Regional Education Program; an easement to drain water from Johnson School; a lawsuit involving a professor with sabbatical leave; the rent for the Opportunities Industrialization Center, Inc.; the Charlottesville High School football stadium; updates on personnel policies; (Reprove case;) bids for a roofing project; and a contract with the Bayly Museum for educational instruction.
    - Correspondence Legal Michael & Dent 1980, 56 items (Box-folder 5:9)
      Correspondents mentioned are R. Lynwood Coffman; Judge James Harry Michael, Jr.; Aaron Mathew Farley and his parents; Office of the Attorney General; Edward L. Hogshire; and Dr. William J. Ellena. Topics of interest are legal cases, namely the case involving a hearing impaired student, Aaron Mathew Farley v. The Honorable S. John Davis; the Charlottesville Learning Exchange v. Richard A. Bergerson; and the Virginia Electric and Power Company agreement. Other topics mentioned are the "Bishop" bill; the Virginia Code; the field and gym at Charlottesville High School; access to student's files; grade promotion requests; tax questions; Yellow Transit Company; school picture and school ring contracts; freezers at Lane High School; and bonuses to bus drivers. There is a resume of Judge James Harry Michael, Jr.
    - Correspondence Legal Dent & Williams; Fein, Deinlein, Petit & Williams 1981, 36 items (Box-folder 6:1)
      Correspondents include Dr. William J. Ellena; Stainback and Scribner; Thomas J. Michie, Jr.; Karen Barket; and Thomas McLernon. Topics mentioned are the Farley case; insurance; Dr. Ellena's contract; legal fees; payroll deductions; tax and social security; by-laws of the Board of Education; alteration of hours; supervision of a softball game; nepotism; payment disputes with architects; School Board committee meetings; the Virginia Freedom of Information Act; and policy for employment application forms.
    - Correspondence Legal Michie, Hamlett, Donato & Lowry 1982 January November, 20 items (Box-folder 6:2)
      Topics mentioned are legal cases such as Robert Danfield Gormes vs. Patrick C. Houchens, Charlottesville School Board v. Rita Wood; School Board v. Adom, Inc.; Hewitt Studios, Inc. v. Central Virginia School Portraits Ltd. and George C. Meador. Other legal issues include handicapped students and buses; spraying to remove Kudzo; city and county for sharing special educational programs, and access to student files.
    - Correspondence Legal Michie, Hamlett, Donato & Lowry 1982-1983 June, 10 items (Box-folder 6:3)
      Topics mentioned are access to student files by a divorced parent, pending case involving Adom, Inc.; and a grading plan and contract for Moore's Creek and Fifth Street.
    - Correspondence Legal from Hogan & Hartson to inform Superintendent of Schools Dr. Joseph McGeehan about new legislation pertinent to education 1989, 5 items (Box-folder 6:4)
      There is a summary of the decisions made during the Supreme Court Term (1988-1989) and its impact on schools. Also included is a copy of the Charlottesville Public Schools Equal Employment Opportunity and Affirmative Action Plan for Personnel Director, Robert R. Hart. There is also a statement of legal fees due Hogan & Hartson.
    - Correspondence Legal Hogan & Hartson 1990, 7 items (Box-folder 6:5)
      Topics mentioned are anti-drug regulations and the Drug-Free Workplace Act of 1988; and a summary of the Supreme Court decisions for 1989-1990. There is correspondence about Judge Dillin and the court case of Donny Brurell Buckley and The Board of School Commissioners of the City of Indianapolis.
    - Correspondence Legal Hogan & Hartson 1991, 8 items (Box-folder 6:6)
      Topics mentioned are a Supreme Court case in Board of Education of Oklahoma City v. Dowell about busing and racial population; Freeman v. Pitts about race and demographic trends; the legalities regarding schools selling student information to the United States Armed Forces. Also included are a summary of the Supreme Court decisions for 1990-1991, a summary of President George Herbert Walker Bush's Civil Rights Act of 1991, and memos about the Hogan & Hartson law firm opening an office in Paris and Prague.
    - Correspondence Legal 1992-1995, 18 items (Box-folder 6:7)
      Topics mentioned are the case of Franklin v. Gwinnett County Public Schools regarding sexual harassment; the case of Freeman v. Pitts; Lee v. Weisman about prayers during graduation ceremonies and a summary of the Supreme Court decisions for 1991-1993; memo about Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas; the case, Harris v. Forklist Systems, Inc. regarding sexual harassment; Office for Civil Rights guidelines for racial harassment; rules from the Securities and Exchange Commission; the Family and Medical Leave Act; gun laws; and students with disabilities.
    B. Correspondence School Board, Superintendents and City Council
  - Correspondence City Improvements 1927
    - Correspondence School Superintendent James G. Johnson 1913-1946, 30 items (Box-folder 7:1)
      Letter from W. H. Wood, Clothier, about Reverend Andrew Allen and an application for the position of teacher; Letter from Dr. Johnson to Charles G. Maphis at the University of Virginia about reading methods and vacation school work. There is a history of the Charlottesville Schools written by James G. Johnson. There is retirement information about Dr. Johnson in an issue of The McGuffey Reader vol. XIV Number 9 and The Sentinel vol. XIX Number 9 (1945)
    - Correspondence School Superintendent Fendall R. Ellis, 1954-1962, 1 notebook (Box-folder 7:2)
      There are many memos to staff, reports on school needs, lists of teachers, and pupil scholarship application forms.
    - Correspondence Superintendent of Schools, Fendall R. Ellis 1961-1964, 1 notebook pt.2 (Box-folder 7:3)
    - Correspondence School Superintendents 1962-1975, 1 notebook pt.1 (Box-folder 7:4)
    - Correspondence School Superintendent William J. Ellena 1975-, 13 items (Box-folder 7:5)
      Proposals and resolution to pave Main Street
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council 1954-1959, 12 items (Box-folder 7:6)
      Correspondents mentioned are Fendall R. Ellis, James E. Bowen, and L. G. Harding. Topics include repairs and additions at Venable, Lane, Jefferson, Burnley-Moran, Clark, and Johnson Schools; radiological detection instruments; bills, budget; and the widening of McIntire Road.
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council 1960-1964, 50 items (Box-folder 7:7)
      Correspondents include James E. Bowen, Bernard J. Haggerty Jr., Fendall R. Ellis, George C. Tramontin, John L. Hammond, Arthur E. Chapman, R. E. Lee and Son, Inc., Lindsay B. Mount, Louie L. Scribner, John R. Ponton, Jack M. Dunnavant, Jr., C. Herbert Paseur, and Robert T. Marsh. Topics include land purchases and improvements for Greenbrier, Clark, Burley, and Jefferson schools; extension of Shamrock Road; school building costs; city and county contract (1950) for a Joint Negro High School; three new junior high schools; enrollment figures and costs; number of "Negro" and "white" teachers; budget (including the statement that no one could understand the budget formula except "Mr. Blount;") student to teacher ratios; drop-outs; architectural fees; old nailed down desks; teacher salaries; and tuition grants.
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council 1965-1967, 27 items (Box-folder 7:8)
      Correspondents include Lindsay B. Mount, Bernard J. Haggerty Jr., Burkett A. Rennolds, James E. Bowen, Jr., George C. Tramontin, Edward W. Rushton, Edward O. McCue, Jr., W. Copley McLean, Hovey S. Dabney, and Paul Saunier, Jr., Topics include land purchases, new schools, and improvements for Burley, Jefferson, Lane, Greenbrier, Clark, Johnson; Buford, and Walker schools; county pupils in city schools, board meeting minutes including the budget; teacher salaries; list of personnel; need for kindergarten programs; busing; transportation of handicapped children; gym rental; and Westminster Study Tutorial.
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council 1968-1973, 34 items (Box-folder 7:9)
      Correspondents include Edward W. Rushton, William J. Ellena, Burkett A. Reynolds; G. A. Vogt, James E. Bowen, Jr., Dr. W. Copley McLean, James Harry Michael, Jr; Laurence A. Brunton, Mitchell Van Yahres, Cole Hendrix, Francis H. Fife, Booker T. Reaves, and Satyendra Huja. Topics mentioned are land purchases and construction for new schools; use of Burley, task force on roads including McIntire Road and 250 bypass; board meeting minutes about budget, appropriation of funds, and interns; enrollment figures; city sidewalks; retirement of James E. Bowen, Jr., Frankfurt International School; bus safety; and the Kimley-Horn report on pupil transportation.
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council (Questions from the Mayors of Charlottesville) 1974-1976, 1 notebook (Box-folder 7:10)
      Correspondents include the Reverend Henry B. Mitchell, Francis Fife, Ronnie Durhan, Richard L. Jennings, Charles L. Barbour, William J. Ellena, and Nancy O'Brien. Topics include City and School Board communication; athletic facilities at Charlottesville High School; mentally impaired children; budget; teacher to student ratios; joint city and school processes, differentiation between administrative and instructive personnel; school owned automobiles; and grants.
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council 1974-1976, 76 items (Box-folder 8:1)